Guide to the Theological Discussion Group Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Theological Discussion Group Papers
1933-1965
RG 43
Yale University Divinity School Library
2.5
(5 boxes)
The majority of the approximately 200 papers were written in connection with the Theological Discussion Group. The papers provide insight into the thoughts and Christian perspective of numerous American theologians and discuss various religious issues of the times. Papers arising from other organizations with similar intent are also contained in the collection. The Theological Discussion Group was established in 1934 as a series of two weekend retreat discussions during the academic year where prominent American theologians met to exchange ideas. The meetings were held at Yale Divinity School and in Washington, D.C.
Theological Discussion Group
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
The majority of the approximately 200 papers included in this record group were written in connection with a Theological Discussion Group which began in 1934 and continued into the early 1960s. Many of the most prominent American theologians of this time period participated in the Group,meeting twice yearly, first at the Yale Divinity School and later in Washington, D.C. The stated intent of the Group as it formed in 1934 was "to hold a series of two week-end 'retreat discussions' during the coming academic year in some relatively secluded place where we could engage in a full, frank and leisurely exchange of ideas...The aim of the discussion will be to discover what is essential and distinctive in the Christian gospel for today." (Box 5, Folder 48)
Scope and Contents
I. Papers by Theologians
II. Documentation of Theological Discussion Groups
In Series I, the papers are arranged alphabetically by author with dates provided when available. Five anonymous papers follow the alphabetical sequence.
Series II contains membership lists, memoranda, correspondence of the discussion groups listed above, and notes of the Theological Discussion Group sessions made by Virginia Corwin Brautigam.
Approximately one-third of the papers in this record group were donated by Virginia Corwin Brautigam, whose notation may also be found on many of the papers themselves.
Individuals Represented in Record Group No. 43 include:
Adams, James Luther (1901- )
Aubrey, Edwin Ewart (1896-1956)
Bainton, Roland Herbert (1894- )
Baker, James Chamberlain, bp. (1879- )
Bennett, John Coleman (1902- )
Bixler, Julius Seelye (1894- )
Blake, Eugene Carson
Bowman, Jon Wick (1894- )
Branscomb, Bennett Harvie (1894- )
Bryson, Lyman (1888- )
Calhoun, Robert Lowry (1896- )
Cavert, Samuel McCrea (1888- )
Corwin, Virginia (1901 - )
Cushman, Robert E.
Kuhn, Helmut (1899- )
Davies, Horton (1916- )
Day, Albert Edward (1884-1973)
Diller, Elliott Van Nostrand
Dinkler, Erich (1909- )
Dinkler-von Schubert, Erika
Dun, Angus, bp. (1892-1971)
Farmer, Herbert Henry (1892- )
Ferre, Nels Frederick Solomon (1908- )
Fisher, Galen Merriam (1873-1955)
Fitch, Robert Elliot (1902- )
Greene, Theodore Meyer (1897-1969)
Hannen, Robert B.
Harkness, Georgia Elma (1891- )
Haroutunian, Joseph (1904-1968)
Harrington, John B.
Hedley, George Percy (1899- )
Hendry, George Stuart (1904- )
Henson, Francis Adams (1906- )
Hopper, Stanley R.
Horton, Walter Marshall (1895-1966)
Hough, Lynn Harold (1877- )
Hume, Theodore Carawell (1904-1943)
Hyslop, Ralph Douglas
Johanson, E. Jerome
Johnson, Sherman Elbridge (1908- )
Kerr, Hugh Thomson (1871-1950)
Knox, John (1900- )
Kraeling, Carl Hermann (1897-1966)
Krumm, John McGill (1913- )
Kruse, Cornelius (1893- )
Lanz, Henry (1886- 1945)
Lehmann, Paul L.
Loomis, Earl Alfred (1921- )
McGiffert, Arthur Cushman (1892- )
McGregor, Daniel Arthur
Mackay, John Alexander (1889- )
Margenau, Henry (1901- )
Mays, Benjamin Elijah (1895- )
Meland, Bernard Eugene (1899- )
Miller, Francis Pickens (1895- )
Miller, Randolph Crump (1910- )
Minear, Paul Sevier (1906- )
Moore, John Morrison (1904- )
Muelder, Walter George (1907- )
Muilenburg, James (1896- )
Murray, John Courtney, S.J. (1904-1967)
Nash, Arnold Samuel
Nelson, John Robert (1920- )
Nelson, William Stuart (1895- )
Niebuhr, Helmut Richard (1894-1962)
Niebuhr, Reinhold (1892-1971)
Nixon, Justin Wroe (1884-1958)
Odell, Morgan Samuel (1894- )
Parker, Pierson
Parsons, Edward Lambe (1868-1960)
Pauck, Wilhelm (1901- )
Piper, Otto A. (1891- )
Pope, Liston (1909-1974)
Reidenbach, Clarence
Robbins, Howard Chandler (1876-1952)
Roberts, David E.
Schubert, Paul (1900-1969)
Shires, Henry Millis (1913- )
Sittler, Joseph (1904- )
Skoglund, John Egnar (1912- )
Slonimsky, Henry (1884- )
Smith, Dwight C.
Smith, John Edwin (1921- )
Spiegelberg, Frederic (1897- )
Steere, Douglas Van (1901- )
Stinnette, Charles Roy (1914- )
Tavard, Georges(1922- )
Thomas, George Finger (1899- )
Thomson, Everett Clay
Tillich, Paul (1886-1965)
Trueblood, David Elton (1908- )
Ungersma, Aaron John (1905- )
Van Dusen, Henry Pitney (1897- )
Vlastos, Gregory
Wedel, Theodore Otto (1892- )
Widgery, Alban Gregory (1887- )
Wieman, Henry Nelson (1884- )
Wilder, Amos Niven (1895- )
Williams, Daniel D.
Wright, George Ernest (1909- )
Zabriskie, Alexander Clinton (1898-1956)
Arrangement
I. Papers by Theologians
II. Documentation of Theological Discussion Groups
Discussion in Christian education; Discussion; Theology; Universities and colleges -- Religion; Authors; Clergy; Deans; Educators; Theologians; Bainton, Roland H. (Roland Herbert), 1894-1984; Bennett, John C. (John Coleman), 1902-1995; Brautigam, Virginia Corwin, 1901-1996; Calhoun, Robert Lowry, 1896-1983; Cavert, Samuel McCrea, 1888-1976; Harkness, Georgia Elma, 1891-1974; Horton, Walter Marshall, 1895-1966; Miller, Francis Pickens, 1895-1978; Miller, Randolph Crump, 1910-2002; Moore, John Morrison, 1904-; Muilenburg, James; Niebuhr, H. Richard (Helmut Richard), 1894-1962; Niebuhr, Reinhold, 1892-1971; Pauck, Wilhelm, 1901-1981; Steere, Douglas V. (Douglas Van), 1901-1995; Tillich, Paul, 1886-1965; Van Dusen, Henry P. (Henry Pitney), 1897-1975; Wilder, Amos N. (Amos Niven), 1895-1993; Yale University. Divinity School; Theological Discussion Group
- Theological Discussion Group Papers, Series I
  - Adams, James Luther (1901- )
    - The Arts and Society, 1955 Nov (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Changing Roles of the Ministry Today:Sociological Factors and Theological Implications, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - The Place of Discipline in Christian Ethics, 1952 Mar (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Aubrey, Edwin Ewart (1896-1956)
    - Christian and Philosophical Ethics, 1941 Nov (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Contributions of American Theology, 1948 Mar (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - The Holy Spirit in Relation to the Religious Community, 1938 Nov (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Humanistic and Anti-Hllmanistic Elements in Modern Christianity, 1953 Nov (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Naturalism and Religious Thought, 1950 Feb (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - What is Essential and Distinctive in the Christian Gospel for Today, 1934 Feb (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bainton, Roland Herbert (1894- )
    - Authority and Religious Knowledge, 1935 Nov (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Comments on Wilhelm Pauck's Paper on The Idea of the Church in Christian History, 1936 Nov (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Grace and Nature in Christianity, 1939 Nov (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Man, God, and the Church in the Age of the Renaissance, 1953 Nov (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - The Sectarian Theory of the Church, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Types and Times of Christian Eschatology, 1941 Mar (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Baker, James C. (1879- )
    - The Strategy of the Church in the United States, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bennett, John Coleman (1902- ), 1943
    - The Christian Basis for Enduring Peace (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Christian Ethics and Communist Ethics, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Christians and the State, 1961 Nov 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - The Christian's Ethical Decision, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - The Church and the Social Community, 1938 Apr (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Limitations of the Church - Inherent and Accidental, 1945 Nov (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - The Meaning of Redemption in Personal and Social Life Today, 1945 Mar (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - The Person of Christ, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Principles and the Situation, 1958 Mar (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - The Problem of Evil, 1937 Nov (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Reinhold Niebuhr's Theological Ethic, 1949 Nov (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - The Relevance of the Ethic of Jesus for Contemporary Life, 1934 Apr (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Summary of Discussions on "Christian Evangelism", 1938 Feb4 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bixler, Julius Seelye (1894- )
    - The Problem of Nature and Grace in Contemporary Secular Thought, 1939 Nov (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Three Contrasts in Contemporary Thought About God, 1937 Nov (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Blake, Eugene Carson
    - Character of Religious Authority in Protestantism, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5A)
    - Conservative Protestant View of the Authority of Scripture, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5A)
  - Bowman, John Wick (1894- )
    - Toward a Christian Understanding of Modern Man (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Branscomb, B. Harvie (1894- )
    - The Biblical Doctrine of the Holy Spirit, 1938 Nov (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - The Ethical Principles of the Gospels, 1941 Nov (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - The Jesus of History, 1934 Apr (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bryson, Lyman (1888- ), n.d.
    - What is a Good Society? (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Calhoun, Robert L. (1896- )
    - Aspects of the Church's Thought About Man: A Historical Outline, 1935 Feb (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Central Christian Affirmations, 1942 Nov 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Christian Theology as Biblical Theology, 1955 Mar (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - The Holy Spirit in the Trinity, 1939 Feb (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - The Theological Doctrine of the Church, 1938 Apr (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Time, Eternity and the End of History, 1940 Nov (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Notes on Hope in the Bible, and in Our Report (This was written for the World Council of Churches) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - What is Distinctive and Essential in the Christian Gospel for Today, 1934 Feb 2-4 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Cavert, Samuel McCrea (1888- )
    - Distinctive Issues in the Relation of Chruch and State Arising from American History, 1937 Jan (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Eschatology and Ethical Decision, 1941 Mar (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Relations Between Roman Catholics and Protestants in America, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - The Resources of the Churches for Economic Change, 1934 Oct (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Corwin, Virginia (1901- ), 1939 Nov
    - A Protestant View of Nature and Grace (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Cushman, Robert E.
    - Plato and Augustine on Time, an abstract (Box 1, Folder 8A)
  - Davies, Horton (1916- )
    - Non-Episcopal Protestantism and the Contemporary Liturical Movement, 1958 Oct (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Day, Albert Edward (1884-1973), n.d.
    - The Form of Revelation (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Diller, Elliott Van N.
    - 'Low Christology' - The Incarnation as Metaphysic and Myth, 1942 Oct (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Mysticism and Ethoics of Lao-Tze, 1950 Nov 3-4 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Wherein Lies the Unity of the Church, 1940 Oct 24 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Dinkler, Erich (1909- )
    - The European View of the American Crisis of Christianity, 1954 Mar (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Principles of Biblical Interpretation, 1954 Nov (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Dinkler-von Schubert, Erika
    - Christianity and Art-A Restatement of Principles (co-authored by Erich Dinkler), 1956 Mar (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Iconography, Liturgy, Theology in the High Middle Ages: The Shrine of St. Elizabeth as an Example, 1955 Nov (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Dun, Angus, Bishop (1892-l971)
    - The Atoning Work of Christ, 1945 Mar (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - What is the Responsibility of the Theologian to the Church, 1938 Apr (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Farmer, Herbert H. (1892- )
    - The Strategy of Christians in Relation to the Present Threat of War, 1934 Oct (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Ferre, Nels F. S. (1908- )
    - A Theological Doctrine of Man, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - The Relation of the Church to the War in the Light of the Christian Faith, 1943 Oct (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Fisher, Galen M. (1873-1955)
    - Hinduism, Buddhism and the Christian Religion Compared (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Ideas of Incarnation in Non-Christian Religions, 1942 Oct (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Fitch, Robert E. (1902- )
    - Christianity and Contemporary Empirical Ethics (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Crisis and Continuity in History (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Reinhold Niebuhr's Philosophy of History, 1950 Apr 21-22 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Seat of Religious Authority, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Greene, Theodore M. (1897-l969)
    - Bases of Christian Belief, 1942 Nov (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Humanistic and Anti-Humanistic Elements in Modern Culture, 1953 Nov (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - The Reasonableness of Christianity, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Hannen, Robert B.
    - Barthian Eschatology and the Modern World (Box 1, Folder 12A)
  - Harkness, Georgia E. (1891- )
    - Eschatology in the Great Poets, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Nature as the Vehicle of Grace, 1940 Mar 2 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Protestant Faith and Ethical Action (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Redemption and Personal Destiny, 1944 Nov (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - What Strategy Should the Church Adopt with Reference to Democracy, 1937 Jan (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Haroutunian, Joseph (1904-1968)
    - The Christian Doctrine of Creatio Ex Nihilo, 1955 Oct 2 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - The Resurrection of the Dead, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Harrington, John B.
    - Mysticism and Ethics of Gandhi (Box 2, Folder 13A)
  - Hedley, George P. (1899- )
    - Hoc Est Corpus Meum: The Jesus of History with Reference to the Incarnation, 1942 Oct (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - The Problem of Evil, 1941 May (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Hendry, George S. ( l904- )
    - Barth's Doctrine of Predestination, 1957 Nov (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Henson, Francis A. (1906- )
    - The Christian Attitude Towards the Marxist Strategy, 1934 Oct (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Hopper, Stanley R
    - Presuppositions in Ethics: Destiny and Freedom in Nicolas Berdyaev (Box 2, Folder 14A)
  - Horton, Walter M. (1895-1966)
    - Contemporary Protestant Theology and the Bible, 1955 Mar (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - The Doctrine of Man II: Salvation, 1949 Nov (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Law and Grace, 1942 Mar (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Nature and Grace in Catholic Theology, 1939 Nov (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Neo-Orthodox Conceptions of Biblical Authority, 1946 Nov. (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Objections to the Doctrine of the Trinity, 1961 Mar (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Revelation, 1935 Nov (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Theological Criteria Bearing on Private Devotional Life, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - What is Essential and Distinctive in the Christian Gospel for Today, 1934 Feb (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Hough, Lynn Harold (1877- )
    - Thinking in a Shaking World, 1934 Apr (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Hume, Theodore C. (1904-1943)
    - Criteria of the Trustworthiness of Authority, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Hyslop, Ralph D.
    - Critique of Section A of Draft Report of the Advisory Com mission on the Theme of the Second Assembly of the World Council of Churches, 1952 May (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Problems Met and Conquered in Specific Unions, 1948 Apr 16-17 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Johanson, E. Jerome
    - Education for Global Brotherhood, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Johnson, Sherman E. (1908- )
    - Critique of and Comments on Section B of Draft Report of the Advisory Commission: Christ as the Hope of the World, in Relation to the World Situation, 1952 May (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Kerr, Hugh T. (1871-1950)
    - The Beginning and the End, 1955 Nov (?) (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Knox, John (1900- )
    - The Eschatology of the New Testament, 1940 Nov (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - "First Draft of Chapter IV", 1943 Apr (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - The Old Testament Ethics, 1941 Nov (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - The Place of Love in New Testament, 1951 Nov (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - The War as Seen from the Point of View of Christian Faith, 1942 Oct (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Kraeling, Carl H. (1897-1966)
    - Pre-Christian Eschatology, 1940 Nov (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Krumm, John McGill (1913- )
    - Eschatology and the Modern Sects (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - The Religious Basis of Christian, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Kruse, Cornelius (1893- )
    - Contemporary Roman Teaching on Religious Liberty and the American Democratic Idea, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - The Philosophical Meaning of Spirit, 1938 Nov (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - What Strategy Should the Church Adopt with Reference to Fascism, 1937 Jan (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Kuhn, Helmut (1899- )
    - The Bible and the Non-Christian Knowledge of God, 1947 Mar (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Lanz, Henry (1886-1945)
    - Immortality of Man, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Lehmann, Paul L.
    - Kant's Conception of Time, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 21A)
  - Loomis, Earl A. (1921- )
    - Non-Verbal Communications - A Psychiatric Concept, and Grace A Theological Concept, 1956 Oct (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - McGiffert, Authur C. (1892- )
    - What is Church?, 1940 Nov (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - McGregor, Daniel A.
    - The Holy Catholic Church, 1936 Nov 2 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - The Holy Spirit and the Church, 1939 Feb (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - What is Essential and Distinctive in the Christian Gospel for Today?, 1934 Feb (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Mackay, John A. (1889- )
    - Historical and Supernatural Elements in Christianity, 1936 Feb (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - The Universal Element in Christianity: With Special Reference to the Christian Approach to the Jew, 1938 Feb (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Margenau, Henry (1901- )
    - Some Thoughts on Science and the Doctrine of Creation, 1955 Nov (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Mays, Benjamin, E. (1895- )
    - Nature, Grace and Community, 1940 Mar (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Meland, Bernard E. (1899- )
    - Love, Mutuality and Justice (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Miller, Francis P. (1895- )
    - American Corruptions of the Meaning of Being a Christian, 1954 Mar (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Christian Ethics and Practical Politics, 1952 Mar (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - The Church as World Community, 1936 Nov (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - The Significance of Jesus for Our Conception of Ultimate Reality, 1934 Feb (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Miller, Randolph C. (1910- )
    - The Authority of Scripture in the Orthodox Roman and Anglican Traditions (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Authority, Scripture and Tradition, 1952 Autumn. (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Christian Ethics and Practical Politics, 1952 Mar (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Christian Hope in Relation to the Church Situation Today, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - The Discovery of Resistance and Resource, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - The Doctrine of Grace: Its Biblical Interpretations, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Empirical Method and its Critics, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - The Jesus of History and the Church (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Orthodox and Roman Views of Scripture, 1949 Nov (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Story of an Average Man, 1952 May (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Minear, Paul S. (1906- )
    - The Kingdom of God in the New Testament, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Moore, John M. (1904- )
    - Authority in Protestantism, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Christian Ethics and Civil Society, 1942 Mar (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Philosophical Analysis and Its Bearing Upon Theology, 1959 Nov (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Scientific Method and Religious Knowledge, 1935 Nov (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Some Anglican Views on the Church, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Muelder, Walter G.(1907- )
    - The Relation of Faith in Science to Faith in Religion, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Muilenburg, James (1896- )
    - The Biblical View of Time, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - The Doctrine of Man - In the Image of God, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - The Ethical Implications of the Covenant, 1951 Nov (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - An Evaluation of the Methods and Assumptions of the Historical Study of the Bible, 1946 Nov (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Hebraism, Judaism, and Christianity (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Murray, John C., S.J. (1904-1967)
    - Contemporary Orientations of Catholic Thought on Church and State in the Light of History, 1949 Apr (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Nash, Arnold Samuel
    - The Relevance of the Social Sciences in the Making of a Moral Judgment, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 27A)
  - Nelson, John Robert (1920- )
    - Christian Theology and the Living Faiths of Men, 1959 Mar (Box 3, Folder 27A)
  - Nelson, William Stuart (1895- )
    - Types of Humanism, 1953 Nov (Box 3, Folder 27A)
  - Niebuhr, Helmut Richard (1894-1962)
    - The Christian Evangel and Social Culture, 1938 Feb (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Kingdom of God and Eschatology (Social Gospel and Barthianism), 1941 Mar (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Man the Sinner, 1935 Feb (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - The Norm of the Christian Character of the Church, 1945 Nov (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Reflections on Faith, Hope and Love, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Reflections on the Christian Theory of History, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Reinhold Niebuhr's Interpretation of History, 1949 Nov (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Types of Christian Ethics, 1942 Mar (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Niebuhr, Reinhold (1892-1971)
    - Love and Law in Protestantism and Catholicism, 1952 Mar (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - The Transcendence of God, 1937 Nov (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Nixon, Justin Wroe (1886-1958)
    - Religious Foundations for Enduring Peace, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Odell, Morgan Samuel (1894- )
    - The Holy Spirit - The Redemptive Influence of God, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Parker, Pierson
    - Current Trends in New Testament Study (Box 3, Folder 31A)
  - Parsons, Edward L. (1868-1960)
    - Autobiography, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Ecumenical Movement: Its History and Theology (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Pauck, Wilhelm (1901- )
    - Christianity in Action (note attached to paper Ethical Realitiy...), 1942 (Box 5, Folder 50)
    - The Dynamics of Protestantism, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - The Holy Spirit in the Doctrine of the Trinity, 1938 Nov (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - The Idea of the Church in Christian History (Parts I and II), 1936 Nov (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Issues Raised by the History of the Doctrine of Redemption, 1945 Mar (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Man as Saved, 1935 Feb (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - What is American in American Theology?, 1948 Mar (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - What is Essential and Distinctive in the Christian Gospel for Today?, 1934 Feb (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Piper, Otto A. (1891- )
    - The Idea of Progress and Christian Eschatology, 1941 Mar (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Pope, Liston (1909-1974)
    - Man in his Contemporary Social Relations in the United States, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Reidenbach, Clarence
    - The Sovereignty of God, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Robbins, Howard C. (1876-1952)
    - The Religious Bases of a Just Peace, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Roberts, David E.
    - Cullmann and Existentialism (Box 3, Folder 34A)
  - Schubert, Erika Dinkler von (see under Dinkler)
  - Schubert, Paul (1900-l969)
    - Contemporary Relevance of Biblical Theology, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - The Context of the Bible: Revelation, Kerygma, Church, Tradition, 1954 Nov (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - The Role of Cult in the Understanding of History According to the New Testament, 1958 Oct (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Shires, Henry M. (1913- )
    - Doctrine of the Church, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Toward a Christian Understanding of Modern Man: The Contribution and Validity of the Renaissance Reformation View (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Sittler, Joseph (1904- )
    - Ethics and the New Testament Style, 1958 Mar (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Skoglund, John E. Revelation and Tradition (1912- ) (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Slonimsky, Henry (1884- )